Guide to the South Africa Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Additional Material, Accession 2000-M-046
  - South African Government
    - Public Protector, Report No. 6 (Special Report), 1997 November 21 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - "TB in South Africa: the People's Plague"[published by the National Department of Health], undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - This is South Africa [a summary of South Africa's yearbook], 1995 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - "Working Conference on the Prevention of Alcohol and Other Drug Abuse amongst the Youth in the Context of the Reconstruction and Development Programme (RDP)", 1995 November 1-2 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - The South African Institute for International Affairs, 1996 November 27 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - South African Institute for Race Relations, 1998, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - South African Jewish Board, undated (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - South African Libertarian Society, 1995 May (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - South African National Gallery, 1997-1998, undated (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - "South African Patriot in Exile," no. 34, undated (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - South African sports [various publications with images of leaders, players, and games], 1995, undated (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Sowetan's Nation Building initiative, 1994 March (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Origins of Intellectual Man--preface to Socrates, 1994 September 22 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Tussentydse Verslag, Clinton V. Du Plessis, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Umxoxi [house journal of the Kwazulu government], 1993 November (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - The United Nations Eco-Volunteer Programme in South Africa, undated (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - "Unity and Peace- Our Challenge," Dawn Nonceba Merle Mokhobo [The Twenty-Third Bertha Solomon Memorial Lecture], 1994 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - University of Cape Town, 1993, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - University of Natal, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - University of Pretoria, 1994 September 1 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - University of Western Cape, 1994, 1996, undated (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - "Uphuhliso"[Department of Development Planning and Local Government newsletter], 1996, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Voter education [materials, training manuals and official guides prepared for Project Vote], 1992, 1994-1996 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Vryheidsfront van Suid Afrika (VF)
    - "Grondwet", undated (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Frontnuues: Tydskrif van die Vryheidsfront, 1997, December 1998 January-March (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - The War Against the Boers, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Worker's Solidarity, Voice of Anarchist-Syndicalism, vol. 2, no. 2, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - World Wildlife Fund South Africa, 1997 February (Box 4, Folder 89)
- Additional Material, Accession 2000-M-057
  This accession consists of material pertaining to the 1999 political elections in South Africa.
  - Political election material, 1997-1999
    - Printed material [brochures, flyers, etc.] (Box 1, Folder 1 - 4)
    - Bumper stickers (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Campaign buttons (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Clothing [shirts, hats] and flags (Box 2)
    - Posters [approximately 56] (Box 3)
    - Posters [approximately 56] (Box 4)
- Additional Material, 1993-1999; Accession 2000-M-140
  - Anti-Apartheid Movement (London), 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Arts and entertainment, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Burial practices, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Government [Constitution], 1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Human rights, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Land reform [Gauteng Province], 1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Additional Material, Accession 2002-M-055
  This accession consists of printed materials and related items pertaining to the World Conference against Racism, Racial Discrimination, Xenophobia, and Related Intolerance, held in Durban, South Africa, from August 28 through September 1, 2001.
  - General information [flyers, brochures] (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
  - NGO Forum materials (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters, reports (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Newspapers (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Posters (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - T-shirts (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Additional Material, Accession 2005-M-053
  This accession consists of printed materials which are alphabetically arranged by organization, personal name, or title of publication.
  - The Africa Fund, 1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - African Christian Democratic Party (ACDP), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - African National Congress (ANC)
    - Conference briefing, 2003 February (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Elections Press Centre, 2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "National Conference in Support of the African National Congress and Other Democratic Forces for a New South Africa: Issue Workshop Reports", 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - National Executive Committee (NEC) Bulletin [2 copies], 2003 January (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Observer Mission to the United Nations, 1992 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Reach Every Voter" [ANC handbook for local election co-ordinators and organisers], undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Transition to Democracy Act", 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Women's Section (UK) Newsletter, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Alternative Information and Development Centre (AIDC), 2002 June (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Association of Concerned African Scholars, 1998 Jun, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Beyond Racism: Embracing an Independent Future" [South Africa 2000 conference materials] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Beyond the Gallery: Art in Public Spaces" [international symposium of public art], 2002 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bezuidenhout, Evita [news clippings], 2000 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cape Times [Madiba at 85, a celebration of Nelson Mandela's birthday], 2003 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Centre for Constitutional Analysis, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Centre for Popular Memory [a coin in honor of Mandela, and various brochures], undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Congress of South African Non-Racial Communities Movement (CoSanCom), undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Educators Against Racism and Apartheid, 1994, Apr, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Government Gazette [Republic of South Africa, No. 15650, complete list of voting stations for 1994 elections], 1994 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - HIV/AIDS, 1997-2000 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Inkatha Freedom Party, 2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "International Conference on the Anglo-Boer War (1899-1902): a Reappraisal", 1999 October 12-15 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Jet [a black American magazine], 1994 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Landless People's Movement (LPM), 2001 November (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "The Many Faces of Nelson Mandela" [stamp collection], 2001 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - National Land Tenure Conference, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Plaatje, Solomom Tshekisho, 1876-1932 [obituary in Diamond Fields Advertiser, supplement], 2001 October 17 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - The Ralph Bunche Institute on the United Nations [occasional papers series, no. XXII], 1994 September (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Sex Worker Education and Advocacy Taskforce (SWEAT) [fact sheets], 2002 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Siddiqui, Professor Rurhsana [photograph taken on the occasion of Nelson Mandela's state visit to Qaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan ], 1992 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Sisulu, Walter [news clippings on his death], 2003 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - South Africa, 1936-1949 [photograph exhibition at the National Museum of African Art, Smithsonian Institution], undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - South African Government. Department of Labour, "Basic Conditions of Employment Act", 1998-2000, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - South African Municipal Workers Union (SAMWU), undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - South African National Youth Commission, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Sowetan [newspaper], 2003 May 8 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Statistics South Africa [key results of census 2001] (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Tourism and historic sites, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Truth and Reconciliation Commission (TRC), 2000 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Umsebenzi [voice of the South African Communist Party], 1995 Dec/1996 Jan, 1996 March (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Workers' Solidarity [a South African anarchist-syndicalist magazine, vol. 2, no. 1], 1996 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Additional Material, 1988-2010; Accession 2011-M-018
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged as received.
  - Elections and Political Parties
    - 2000 Election Roster-West Cape Province (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "African National Congress-List of candidates for the 1999 elections as submitted to the IEC on 3 May 1999", 1999 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ten Good Reasons Why You Should Support the Progressive Party, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Two copies. One in English; one in Dutch (Tien Goeie Redes Waarom U Die Progressiewe Party Behoort Te Ondersteun)
    - United Christian Democratic Party (UCDP), includes manifesto and history (2 copies), Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - ANC-2004 Manifesto: A People's Contract to Create Work and Fight Poverty (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Souvenir Supplement to This Day, "Celebrating 10 years of Parliament", 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - ANC- A People's Contract to Create Work and Fight Poverty, 2004 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Statement of the National Executive Committee of the African National Congress on the occasion of the 92nd anniversary of the ANC.
    - New Labour Party Election Manifesto, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - African Christian Democratic Party Manifesto, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Together, IFP (Inkatha Freedom Party) National Manifesto for the 2004 election (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Independent Democrats (ID) Election Manifesto brochure, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - NNP Manifesto, (New National Party), 2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      New National Party/Nuwe Nasionale Party. Manifesto is in both languages.
    - The Green Party of South Africa campaign pamphlet, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - VF Verkiesing 2004 election manifesto (Freedom Front Plus) ) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - UDM Election Manifesto, (United Democratic Movement), 2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Peaceful Change Now" bumper sticker, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Pan Africanist Congress of Azania (PAC) Election Manifesto, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Provisional ballots from the 1994 presidential election (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Three different ballots depicting candidates from different geographic locations.
  - Publications and memorabilia
    - Gold and diamond mining map-Gauteng, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - No Longer At This Address: Navigating Post-Apartheid Identities, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Program for an exhibit at the Durban Art Gallery that examines the history of older colonial names, and the people and events behind the new names.
    - Map of Soweto South Western Township, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Time to Act: The Recommendations of the Truth and Reconciliation Commission, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "eThekwini ECOPEACE Sustainable Lifestyles Policy", 2003 June (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "eThekwini ECOPEACE Values", 2003 April (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Sasi Nuus, 2005 December (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Truth and Reconciliation Commission: Written submission from the Anglo American Corporation of South Africa Limited", 1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Table Mountain Park, map three, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - The San of Southern Africa: Heritage and Intellectual Property, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      The term "San" refers to indigenous people of southern Africa.
    - "Nasionale Aksie: Jou toekoms is hier", Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
      The National Action (more commonly known by its Afrikaans name, Nasionale Aksie), was a short-lived South African political party.
    - South African Sports Action, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      A special edition paying tribute to Nelson Mandela.
    - Lesley Beake, award nominee, South African Children's Book Forum, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The TRC: Ten Years On, 2006 April 20-21 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Conference packet of the Truth and Reconciliation Commission and the Institute for Justice and Reconciliation.
    - Lewis, David Robert
      David Robert Lewis (born 1968) is a South African editor, writer and artist.
      - "Essays in Media & Cultural Studies, 1991-2005", Circa 2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - "Supersized Media!", Undated
    - The Free Market Foundation of Southern Africa, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Address on reducing unemployment and poverty, by Dr. Sam Motsuenyane, president of the Free Market Foundation.
    - "AFRO" football cards/logos, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - St George's Cathedral Cape Town: church service bulletin, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Die Suid-Afrikaanse Instituut Van Internasionale Aangeleenthede/The South African Institute of International Affairs
      - "The International Road Ahead for South Africa," address by F. W. De Klerk, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - "Peacemaking and Democracy in Southern Africa: An American View," address by William Lacy Swing, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - "A Time for Greatness," address by Margaret Thatcher, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Land Tenure: A Time Bomb Ticking In South Africa, by Godfrey Dunkley, 1991 March (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - The Story of Bibi Dawood of Worcester, by Zubeida Jaffer, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Handbag decorated with images of Nelson Mandela, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Cap with Azanian Peoples' Organization (AZAPO) logo, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Fabrics decorated with images of Nelson Mandela, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Additional Material, 2002; Accession 2014-M-022
  This accession consists of two Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgendered (LGBT) publications from South Africa: Detail Cape Town, and Out in Africa.
  - Detail Cape Town, 2002 August (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Out In Africa, 2002 February 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional material, 1990-2014; Accession 2015-M-001
  - Printed material, 1990-2014 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Printed material accompanying CDs, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    See also: boxes 3-5.
  - Textiles
    - Printed fabric remnant featuring Nelson Mandela and ANC, Circa 1995 (Box 2)
    - Printed fabric remnant featuring Jacob Zuma and ANC, Circa 2007 (Box 2)
    - Zuma for ANC President campaign tee shirt, Circa 2007 (Box 2)
  - Audio recordings
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
    Copies of commercially produced audiovisual materials contained in this collection cannot be made for researcher use outside of the repository.
    See also: box 1, folder 3.
    - Misery/Tritesse [commercially produced], 2009; 1 (Box 3)
    - Mister Motherfucker [commercially produced], 2009; 1 (Box 4)
    - Screaming Bastard Child [commercially produced], 2009; 1 (Box 5)
  - Nelson Mandela
    - 2008 exhibit material, 1990-2008 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Includes reproductions of photographs dating from 1940s on.
    - Mandela and sports, 2004-2010 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Publications on 80th and 90th birthdays, life, and death of Mandela, 1998-2013 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Apartheid Museum poster of Mandela exhibit, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Nelson Mandela Day brochure and flyer, 2012 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Postcards with quotations from Mandela, Circa 2010 (Box 6, Folder 4)